part 2 chapter 4.
Winston looked around the shabby little room above Mr Charrington's shop.
Beside the window the enormous bed was made up, with ragged blankets and a coverless bolster.
The old-fashioned clock with the 12-hour face was ticking away on the mantelpiece.
In the corner, on the gate leg table, the glass paperweight which he had bought on
his last visit gleamed softly out of the half Darkness
In the fender was a batter to tin oil stove a saucepan and two cups, provided
by Mr cherrington Winston lit the burner and set a pan of water to boil.
He had brought an envelope full of Victory Coffee and some saccharine tablets.
The clock's hands said 1720 it was 1920 really.
She was coming at 1930.
Folly, folly, his heart kept saying: conscious, gratuitous, suicidal folly. Of
all the crimes that a Party member could commit, this one was the least possible to conceal.
Actually the idea had first floated into his head in the form of a vision of the
glass paperweight mirrored by the surface of the gate leg table.
As he had foreseen, Mr Charrington had made no difficulty about letting the room.
He was obviously glad of the few dollars that it would bring him. Nor did he seem
shocked or become offensively knowing when it was made clear that Winston
wanted the room for the purpose of a love affair.
Instead he looked into the middle distance and spoke in generalities, with
so delicate and heirs to give the impression that he had become partly invisible
the Privacy, he said, was a very valuable thing.
Everyone wanted a place where they could be alone occasionally.
And when they had such a place, it was only common courtesy in anyone else who
knew of it to keep his knowledge to himself.
He even, seeming almost to fade out of existence as he did so, added that there
were two entries to the house, one of them threw the backyard which gave on an alley.
Under the window somebody was singing.
Winston peeped out, secure in the protection of the muslin curtain.
The June sun was still high in the sky, and in the sun-filled court below a
monstrous woman, solid as a Norman pillar, with brawny red forearms and a sacking
apron strapped about her middle, was stumping to and fro between a wash tub
and a clothesline pegging out a series of square white things which Winston
recognized as babies' diapers.
Whenever her mouth was not corked with clothes pegs she was singing in a powerful contralto:
It was only an hopeless fancy, It passed like an April die But a look and a word
in the dreams they stirred They have stolen my heart away The Dune had been haunting London for
weeks past. It was one of countless similar songs published for the benefit
of the Pearls by a subsection of the Music Department.
The words of these songs were composed without any human intervention whatever
on an instrument known as a versificator.
But the woman sang so tunefully is to turn the dreadful rubbish into an almost pleasant sound.
He could hear the woman singing and the scrape of her shoes on the flagstones,
and the cries of the children in the street, and somewhere in the far distance
a faint roar of traffic, and yet the room seemed curiously silent, thanks to the
absence of a telescreen.
Folly, folly, folly! he thought again he It was inconceivable that they could
frequent this place for more than a few weeks without being caught.
But the temptation of having a hiding place that was truly their own, indoors
and near at hand, had been too much for both of them.
For some time after their visit to the church belfry it had been impossible to
arrange meetings. Working hours had been drastically increased in anticipation of Hate Week.
It was more than a month distant, but the enormous, complex preparations that it
entailed were throwing extra work onto everybody.
Finally both of them managed to secure a free afternoon on the same day.
They had agreed to go back to the clearing in the wood.
On the evening beforehand they met briefly in the street.
As usual Winston hardly looked at Julia as they drifted towards one another in
the crowd, but from the short glance he gave her it seemed to him that she was
paler than usual.
'It's all off,' she murmured as soon as she judged it safe to speak. 'Tomorrow, I mean.'
'What?'
'Tomorrow afternoon. I can't come.'
'Why not?'
'Oh, the usual reason it started early this time.'
For a moment he was violently angry.
During the month that he had known her the nature of his desire for her had
changed. At the beginning there had been little true sensuality in it.
Their first love- making had been simply an act of the will.
But after the second time it was different.
The smell of her hair, the taste of her mouth, the feeling of her skin seemed to
have got inside him, or into the air all around him.
She had become a physical necessity, something that he not only wanted but
felt that he had a right to. When she said that she could not come, he had the
feeling that she was cheating him.
But just at this moment the crowd pressed them together and their hands accidentally met.
She gave the tips of his fingers a quick squeeze that seemed to invite not to
desire but affection struck him that when one lived with a woman this particular disappointment
must be a normal, recurring event; and a deep tenderness, such as he had not felt
for her before, suddenly took hold of him.
He wished that they were a married couple of ten years' standing. He wished
that he were walking through the streets with her just as they were doing now, but
openly and without fear, talking of trivialities and buying odds and ends
for the household. He wished above all that they had some place where they
could be alone together without feeling the obligation to make love every time they met.
It was not actually at that moment, but at some time on the following day, that
the idea of renting Mr cherrington's room had occurred to him.
When he suggested it to Julia she had agreed with unexpected readiness.
Both of them knew that it was lunacy.
It was as though they were intentionally stepping nearer to their graves.
As he sat waiting on the edge of the bed he thought again of the sellers of the
Ministry of Love. It was curious how that predestined horror moved in and out of
one's consciousness.
There it lay, fixed in future times preceding death as surely as 99 precedes
100.. One could not avoid it, but one could perhaps postpone it: and yet
instead, every now and again, by a conscious willful act, one chose to
shorten the interval before it happened.
At this moment there was a quick step on the stairs. Julia burst into the room. She
was carrying a tool bag of coarse brown canvas, such as he had sometimes seen her
carrying to and fro at the Ministry. He started forward to take her in his arms,
but she disengaged herself rather hurriedly, partly because she was still holding the tool bag
Half a second,' she said. 'Just let me show you what I've brought.
Did you bring some of that filthy Victory Coffee?
I thought you would. You can chuck it away again, because we shouldn't be
needing it. Look here.'
She fell on her knees, threw open the bag and tumbled out some spanners and a
screwdriver that filled the top part of it.
Underneath were a number of neat paper packets.
The first packet that she passed to Winston had a strange and yet vaguely familiar feeling.
It was filled with some kind of heavy sand like stuff which yielded wherever you touched it.
'It isn't sugar? he said.
'Real sugar. Not saccharin sugar.
And here's a loaf of bread— —proper white bread, not our bloody stuff— —and a little
pot of jam. And here's a tin of milk— —but
look! This is the one I'm really proud of.
I had to wrap a bit of sacking around it, because———'
But she did not need to tell him why she had wrapped it up. The smell was already
filling the room, a rich hot smell which seemed like an emanation from his early
childhood, but which one did occasionally meet with even now, blowing down a
passageway before a door slammed, or diffusing itself mysteriously in a
crowded street, sniffed for an instant and then lost again.
'It's coffee,' he murmured, 'real coffee.'
'It's in a Party coffee. There's a whole kilo here,' she said.
'How did you manage to get hold of all these things?'
'It's all in a Party stuff.
There's nothing those swine don't have, nothing.
But of course waiters and servants and people pinch things, and— —look, I got a
little packet of tea as well.'
Winston had squatted down beside her. He tore open a corner of the packet.
'It's real tea. Not blackberry leaves.'
'There's been a lot of tea about lately.
They've captured India, or something,' she said vaguely.
'But listen, dear. I want you to turn your back on me for three minutes. Go and sit
on the other side of the bed. Don't go too near the window. And don't turn
around till I tell you.'
Winston gazed abstractedly through the muslin curtain. Down in the yard the red
armed woman was still marching to and fro between the wash tub and the line.
She took two more pegs out of her mouth and sang with deep feeling:
They say that time heals all things, They say you can always forget; But the smiles
and the tears across the ears They twist my art strings yet!
She knew the whole dribbling song by heart, it seemed. Her voice floated upward
with the sweet summer air, very tuneful, charged with a sort of happy melancholy.
One had the feeling that she would have been perfectly content, if the June
evening had been endless and the supply of clothes inexhaustible, to remain there
for a thousand years, pegging out diapers and singing rubbish.
It struck him as a curious fact that he had never heard a member of the Party
singing alone and spontaneously. It would even have seemed slightly unorthodox, a
dangerous eccentricity, like talking to oneself.
Perhaps it was only when people were somewhere near the starvation level that
they had anything to sing about.
'You can turn around now,' said Julia.
He turned round, and for a second almost failed to recognize her.
What he had actually expected was to see her naked.
But she was not naked.
The transformation that had happened was much more surprising than that. She had
painted her face.
She must have slipped into some shop in the proletarian quarters and bought
herself a complete set of makeup materials.
Her lips were deeply reddened, her cheeks rouged, her nose powdered; there was even
a touch of something under the eyes to make them brighter.
It was not very skillfully done, but Winston's standards in such matters were not high.
He had never before seen or imagined a woman of the Party with cosmetics on her face.
The improvement in her appearance was startling.
With just a few dabs of color in the right places she had become not only
very much prettier, but, above all, far more feminine.
Her short hair and boyish overalls merely added to the effect.
As he took her in his arms a wave of synthetic violets flooded his nostrils.
He remembered the half darkness of a basement kitchen, and a woman's cavernous mouth.
It was the very same sense that she had used; but at the moment it did not seem
to matter sent two he said.
'Yes, dear sent to And you know what I'm going to do next?
I'm going to get hold of a real woman's frock from somewhere and wear it instead
of these bloody trousers.
I'll wear silk stockings and high-heeled shoes! In this room I'm going to be a
woman, not a Party comrade.'
They flung their clothes off and climbed into the huge mahogany bed.
It was the first time that he had stripped himself naked in her presence.
Until now he had been too much ashamed of his pale and Amiga body, with the
varicose veins standing out on his calves in the discolored patch over his ankle.
There were no sheets, but the blanket they lay on was thread bare and smooth,
and the size and springiness of the bed astonished both of them.
'It's sure to be full of bugs, but who cares?' said Julia.
One never saw a double bed nowadays, except in the homes of the pros
Winston had occasionally slept in one in his boyhood: Julia had never been in one
before, so far as she could remember.
Presently they fell asleep for a little while.
When Winston woke up at the hands of the clock had crept round to nearly nine. He
did not stir, because Julia was sleeping with her head in the crook of his arm.
Most of her makeup had transferred itself to his own face or the bolster,
but a light stain of rouge still brought out the beauty of her cheekbone.
A yellow ray from the sinking sun fell across the foot of the bed and lighted
up the fireplace, where the water in the pan was boiling fast.
Down in the yard the woman had stopped singing, but the fan shouts of children
floated in from the street.
He wondered vaguely whether in the abolished past it had been a normal
experience to lie in bed like this, in the cool of a summer evening, a man and a
woman with no clothes on, making love when they chose, talking of what they
chose, not feeling any compulsion to get up, simply lying there and listening to
peaceful sounds outside. Surely there could never have been a time when that seemed ordinary?
Julia woke up, rubbed her eyes and raised herself on her elbow to look at the oil stove
Half that water's boiled away,' she said.
'I'll get up and make some coffee in another moment. We've got an hour. What
time do they cut the lights off at your flats 23 30.
It's 23 at the hostel. But you have to get in earlier than that, because hey Get
out, you filthy brute!'
She suddenly twisted herself over in the bed, seized a shoe from the floor and
sent it hurtling into the corner with a boyish jerk of her arm, exactly as he had
seen her fling the dictionary at Goldstein, that morning during the Two Minutes Hate.
'What was it?' he said in surprise.
'A rat. I saw him stick his beastly nose out of the wainscoting. There's a hole
down there. I gave him a good fright, anyway.'
'Rats!' murmured Winston. 'In this room!'
'They're all over the place,' said Julia indifferently as she lay down again.
'We've even got them in the kitchen at the hostel.
Some parts of London are swarming with them. Did you know they attacked children?
Yes, they do. In some of these streets a woman don't leave a baby alone for two minutes.
It's the great huge brown ones that do it. And the nasty thing is that the
brutes always— 'Don't go on!' said Winston, with his eyes tightly shut.
'Dearest! You've gone quite pale. What's the matter? Do they make you feel sick?'
'Of all the horrors in the world— —a rat!'
She pressed herself against him and wound her limbs around him, as though to
reassure him with the warmth of her body.
He did not reopen his eyes immediately.
For several moments he had had the feeling of being back in a nightmare
which had recurred from time to time throughout his life.
It was always very much the same. He was standing in front of a wall of darkness,
and on the other side of it there was something unendurable, something too
dreadful to be faced. In the dream his deepest feeling was always one of
self-deception, because he did in fact know what was behind the wall of darkness.
With a deadly effort, like wrenching a piece out of his own brain, he could even
have dragged the thing into the open.
He always woke up without discovering what it was somehow it was connected with what Julia
had been saying when he cut her short.
'I'm sorry,' he said; 'it's nothing. I don't like rats, that's all.'
'Don't worry, dear, we're not going to have the filthy brutes in here. I'll stuff the
hole with a bit of sacking before we go.
And next time we come here I'll bring some plaster and bang it up properly.'
Already the black incident of panic was half forgotten Feeling slightly ashamed of himself, he
sat up against the Bed Head Julia got out of bed, pulled on her
overalls and made the coffee.
The smell that rose from the saucepan was so powerful and exciting that they
shut the window lest anybody outside should notice it and become inquisitive.
What was even better than the taste of the coffee was the silky texture given
to it by the sugar, a thing Winston had almost forgotten after years of saccharine.
With one hand in her pocket and a piece of bread and jam in the other, Julia
wandered about the room, glancing in differently at the bookcase pointing out
the best way of repairing the gate leg table, plumping herself down in the
ragged arm chair to see if it was comfortable, and examining the absurd
12-hour clock with a sort of tolerant amusement.
She brought the glass paperweight over to the bed to have a look at it in a
better light.
He took it out of her hand, fascinated, as always, by the soft rain watery
appearance of the glass.
'What is it, do you think?' said Julia.
'I don't think it's anything— —I mean, I don't think it was ever put to any use.
That's what I like about it. It's a little chunk of history that they've
forgotten to alter. It's a message from a hundred years ago, if one knew how to read it.'
'And that picture over there'— '—she nodded at the engraving on the opposite wall—'
—'would that be a hundred years old?'
'More 200 ideas say. One can't tell. It's impossible to discover the age of anything nowadays.'
She went over to look at it.
'Here's where that brute stuck his nose out,' she said, kicking away and squirting
immediately below the picture.
'What is this place? I've seen it before somewhere.'
'It's a church, or at least it used to be some Clement Danes its name was.'
The fragment of rhyme that Mr cherrington had taught him came back
into his head, and he added half nostalgically Oranges and lemons," say the bells are
Saint Clements To his astonishment she kept the line:
'You owe me three farthings,' say the bells of Saint Martins When will you pay me?'
say the bells of Old Bailey— 'I can't remember how it goes on after
that. But anyway I remember it ends up, "Here comes a candle to light you to bed,
here comes a chopper to chop off your head!"'
It was like the two halves of a counter sign But there must be another line after 'the
bells of Old bayley Perhaps it could be dug out of Mr Charrington's memory, if he was suitably
prompted.
'Who taught you that?' he said.
'My grandfather. He used to say it to me when I was a little girl. He was
vaporized when I was eight— —at any rate, he disappeared.
I wonder what a lemon was,' she added inconsequently. 'I've seen oranges. They're
a kind of round yellow fruit with a thick skin.'
'I can remember lemons,' said Winston. 'They were quite common in the 50s They were
so sour that it set your teeth on edge even to smell them.'
'I bet that picture's got bugs behind it,' said Julia. 'I'll take it down and give it
a good clean someday I suppose it's almost time we were leaving. I must start
washing this paint off. What a boar I'll get the lipstick off your face afterwards.'
Winston did not get up for a few minutes more.
The room was darkening. He turned over towards the light and leg gazing into
the glass paperweight.
The inexhaustibly interesting thing was not the fragment of coral but the
interior of the glass itself.
There was such a depth of it, and yet it was almost as transparent as air.
It was as though the surface of the glass had been the arch of the sky,
enclosing a tiny world with its atmosphere complete.
He had the feeling that he could get inside it, and that in fact he was inside
it, along with the mahogany bed and the gate leg table, and the clock and the
steel engraving and the paperweight itself.
The paperweight was the room he was in, and the coral was Julia's life in his
own, fixed in a sort of eternity at the heart of the crystal